Guide to the Spanish Dance Society USA Chapter records, 1982-1993 MS2039
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Spanish Dance Society USA Chapter records
1982-1993
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Grut, Marina
MS2039
2.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains programs, newsletters, teaching manual, syllabi, playbills photographs, videocassettes, brochures, postcards, performance schedules, and articles documenting the activities of the society during 1982-93. The three videocassettes are of performances given by the society in the Washington, DC area.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Spanish Dance Society USA is a chapter of the international organization, the Spanish Dance Society. The society was founded in South Africa in 1965 by a group of dance teachers who wanted to set a standard for Spanish dance instruction and performance. What was created was a structured method of training and certification involving six junior grades, three senior grades, and two levels for teacher certification. Instruction includes basic dance maneuvers, as well as knowledge of the music, costumes, and history of the dances.
The Spanish Dance Society has chapters in Australia, Brazil, Cyprus, Greece, Italy, Malta, New Zealand, South Africa, Spain, England, and the United States of America. The USA chapter was founded by Marina Keet in Washington, DC in 1982. The classes are taught at the George Washington University and considered part of the regular curriculum. Dancers from the Washington, DC chapter have performed at the Spanish Embassy, the Smithsonian Institution, the Kennedy Center, and the Julliard School in New York, as well as other prominent institutions throughout the United States and the world.
Marina Keet Grut is one of the founding members of the Spanish Dance Society. She studied and taught at the Ballet School at the University of Cape Town in South Africa during the 1960s and most of the 1970s. In 1977, Mrs. Keet Grut and her husband moved to Italy, where she founded the first chapter of the society outside of South Africa. After moving to the United States with her husband in 1981, Marina Keet Grut founded the USA chapter in Washington, DC the following year. While in DC, Mrs. Keet Grut taught dance at The George Washington University, organized Society events, and worked with other teachers to revise the instruction syllabi.
Marina Keet Grut has taught Spanish dance throughout Europe and the United States. The Hispanic Institute for the Performing Arts has honored her, as well as the King of Spain, who named her as a Dame of the Order of Queen Isabel of Spain, which is the highest honor bestowed upon non-Spaniards. She is the author of two books, Spanish Dance (1975), and The History of Ballet in South Africa (1981), and of numerous papers and articles. She now lives in London and is actively involved with the European branch of the Spanish Dance Society.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains programs, newsletters, teaching manual, syllabi, playbills photographs, videocassettes, brochures, postcards, performance schedules, and articles. These records document the activities of the society during 1982-93. The three videocassettes are of performances given by the society in the Washington, DC area.
The Spanish Dance Society USA Records are part of the Dance Archives of the Greater Washington Region. The Archives was established in 1993 by Nancy Diers Johnson, Ed.D., Associate Professor of Dance, and the Gelman Library of The George Washington University. The Dance Archives of the Greater Washington Region collects, preserves and makes accessible the documentary heritage of all forms and types of dance.
The Spanish Dance Society USA Records were placed on loan with the Special Collections Department by Marina Keet Grut and Nancy Sedgwick, founder and chairperson respectively, of the USA chapter of the society in November 1994.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Administrative records, Audiovisual materials, and Miscellaneous.
Photographs; Dance; Washington (D.C.); Videocassettes; Johnson, Nancy Diers; Spanish Dance Society USA; Grut, Marina
- Administrative records, undated; MS2039 Series 1; 1 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of articles, programs, newsletters, instruction syllabi, as wells as a board kit, performance schedules, and planning material for the 25th Anniversary of the society and material related to the administrative activities of the Spanish Dance Society USA.
  - Administrative Files: Board Kit (2 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Administrative Files: Corporate Kit, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Files: Three year long range plan, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Files: Information packet about the society, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Administrative Files: Playbills/programs, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Administrative Files: Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Files: Performance schedules, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Files: Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Files: Program proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Files: Newsletters/reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Files: International Center for Spanish Dance course material, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Files: Planning material for the 25th anniversary of the society, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Administrative Files: Society of Dance History Scholars Conference material and papers presented by Maria Keet, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Files: Biographical information about Maria Keet, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Teaching Material: Introductory syllabus, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Teaching Material: Teacher's manual, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Teaching Material: Junior theory syllabus, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Teaching Material: Junior syllabus, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Teaching Material: Junior syllabus and theory: ingress - quinto ano (2 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Material: Primer ano estudiante syllabus, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Teaching Material: Music syllabus, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Audiovisual materials, 1987-1992; MS2039 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series contains both black and white and color photographs and videocassettes of society performances. The photographs represented society dancers, including Nancy Heller, Ziva Cohen, and Nancy Sedgwieck, among others, performing dances such as the Mortitxol, La Danza Charra, and Bolero de l'Alcudia de Carlet. The videocassettes are of performances at the Marvin Center Theater and the Kennedy Center. The videocassettes date from 1987-92.
  - Photographs: Color 8" x 11"of the Mortitxol, photographed by Victor Cohen, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs: Color 8" x 11"of the Mortitxol, photographed by Victor Cohen, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs: Color 8" x 11"of the Mortitxol, photographed by Victor Cohen, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs: Color 8" x 11" of the La Danza Charra, photographed by Victor Cohen, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs: Color 8" x 11" of the Charrada, photographed by Victor Cohen, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs: Color 8" x 11" of the Bolero de l'Alcudia de Carlet, photographed by Victor Cohen, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photographs: Black and white 8" x 10"of the Bolero de l'Alcudia de Carlet, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs: Black and white 8" x 10" of the Jarabe Tapatio, photographed by Ken Cobb, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photographs: Black and white 8" x 10" of Nancy Heller, Lourdes Elias, and Nancy Sedgwick, photographed by Ken Cobb, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: Black and white 8" x 10" of Jaime Coronado and Ziva Cohen, photographed by Victor Cohen, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Photographs: Black and white 8" x 10" of Nancy Heller, Nancy Sedgwick, and Lourdes Elias, photographed by Ken Cobb, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Photographs: Color 4" x 6" of Jaime Coronado, Ziva Cohen, Nancy Heller, and Nancy Sedgwick, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photographs: Color 4" x 6" of Nancy Sedgwick, Danielle Polen, Ziva Cohen, and Nancy Heller, photographed by Ken Cobb, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Videocassettes: George Washington University Marvin Theater performance, guest artists Marina Lorca and Roberto Amaral, November 1987. Kennedy Center performance, guest artists Marina Lorca and Roberto Amaral, May 20, 1991. National Geographic Performance, April, 1992, 1987 November-1992 May (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous, 1988-1992; MS2039 Series 3; 1 Linear feet
  This series contains published material collected by the society, ephemera, scrapbooks of society activities dating from 1987-89.
  - Published Material: Hispanic Institute for the Performing Arts Guide to Hispanic Cultural World 1989 edition (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Published Material: Las Falas, by Martín Domínguez Barberá, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Published Material: Cancionero Musical de la Provincia de Valencia, by Salvador Segui, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Published Material: Fall 1988 Course Guide published by the George Washington University Student Association, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous: Invitation, RSVP card and envelope to an performance of the Spanish Dance Society at the Embassy of Spain, 1991 June 12 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous: Map of Spain and Portugal, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous: Nancy Sedgwick's Maestra de Baile Espanol Theory Examination, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous: Brochure, postcards, and press reviews about the African Heritage Center Dancers and Drummers, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous: Business card of Boulton B Miller, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Artifact: Porcelain statue of a female Spanish dancer, which measures 8 ¼" (21cm) tall with a 4 7/8" (12cm) diameter base. The markings in the bottom of the statue indicate that it was made by the Santa Rufina Company in Valencia, Spain, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Artifact: Medal with Spanish writing, which measures 1/8" (.5cm) thick with a 2 ¼" (6cm) diameter. On one side is the image of a rose with a flag and the phrase "JOCS FLORALS DE LA CIUTAT I REGNE DE VALENCIA" and "1983 CENTENARI." On the other side is the image of a bat and a coat of arms and the phrases "PEL FIL TRAUREM LO CAPDELL" and "LO RAT PENAT." The medal is stored in a satin-lined gray box, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)